In this video we'll talk about
在这段视频中
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
matrix addition and subtraction,
我们将讨论矩阵的加法和减法运算
as well as how to
以及如何进行
multiply a matrix by a
数和矩阵的乘法
number, also called Scalar Multiplication.
也就是标量乘法
Let's start an example.
让我们从下面这个例子开始
Given two matrices like these,
假设有这样两个矩阵
let's say I want to add them together.
如果想对它们做求和运算
How do I do that?
应该怎么做呢？
And so, what does addition of matrices mean?
或者说 矩阵的加法到底是如何进行的？
It turns out that if you
答案是
want to add two matrices, what
如果你想将两个矩阵相加
you do is you just add
你只需要将这两个矩阵的
up the elements of these matrices one at a time.
每一个元素都逐个相加
So, my result of adding
因此 两个矩阵相加
two matrices is going to
所得到的结果
be itself another matrix and
就是一个新的矩阵
the first element again just by
它的第一个元素
taking one and four and
是1和4相加的结果
multiplying them and adding them together, so I get five.
因此我们得到5
The second element I get
接下来是第二个元素
by taking two and two
用2和2相加
and adding them, so I get
因此得到4
four; three plus three
然后是3加0得到3
plus zero is three, and so on.
以此类推
I'm going to stop changing colors, I guess.
这里我用不同颜色区别一下
And, on the right is open
接下来右边这一列元素
five, ten and two.
就是0.5 10和2
And it turns out you can
这里大家不难发现
add only two matrices that are of the same dimensions.
只有相同维度的两个矩阵才能相加
So this example is
对于这个例子而言
a three by two matrix,
这是一个3行2列的矩阵
because this has 3
也就是说矩阵的行数为3
rows and 2 columns, so it's 3 by 2.
列数是2 因此是3行2列
This is also a 3
第二个矩阵
by 2 matrix, and the
也是一个3行2列的矩阵
result of adding these two
因此这两个矩阵相加的结果
matrices is a 3 by 2 matrix again.
也是一个3行2列的矩阵
So you can only add
所以你只能将相同维度的矩阵
matrices of the same
进行相加运算
dimension, and the result
同时 所得到的结果
will be another matrix that's of
将会是一个新的矩阵
the same dimension as the ones you just added.
这个矩阵与相加的两个矩阵维度相同
Where as in contrast, if you
反过来
were to take these two matrices, so this
如果你想将这样两个矩阵相加
one is a 3 by
这是一个3行2列的矩阵
2 matrix, okay, 3 rows, 2 columns.
行数为3 列数为2
This here is a 2 by 2 matrix.
而这一个是2行2列的矩阵
And because these two matrices
那么由于这两个矩阵
are not of the same dimension,
维度是不相同的
you know, this is an error,
这就出现错误了
so you cannot add these
所以我们不能将它们相加
two matrices and, you know,
也就是说
their sum is not well-defined.
这两个矩阵的和是没有意义的
So that's matrix addition.
这就是矩阵的加法运算
Next, let's talk about multiplying matrices by a scalar number.
接下来 我们讨论矩阵和标量的乘法运算
And the scalar is just a,
这里所说的标量
maybe a overly fancy term for,
可能是一个复杂的结构
you know, a number or a real number.
或者只是一个简单的数字 或者说实数
Alright, this means real number.
标量在这里指的就是实数
So let's take the number 3 and multiply it by this matrix.
如果我们用数字3来和这个矩阵相乘
And if you do that, the result is pretty much what you'll expect.
那么结果是显而易见的
You just take your elements
你只需要将矩阵中的所有元素
of the matrix and multiply
都和3相乘
them by 3, one at a time.
每一个都逐一与3相乘
So, you know, one
因此 1和3相乘
times three is three.
结果是3
What, two times three is
2和3相乘
six, 3 times 3
结果是6
is 9, and let's see, I'm
最后3乘以3得9
going to stop changing colors again.
我再换一下颜色
Zero times 3 is zero.
0乘以3得0
Three times 5 is 15, and 3 times 1 is three.
3乘以5得15 最后3乘以1得3
And so this matrix is the
这样得到的这个矩阵
result of multiplying that matrix on the left by 3.
就是左边这个矩阵和3相乘的结果
And you notice, again,
我们再次注意到
this is a 3 by 2
这是一个3行2列的矩阵
matrix and the result is
得到的结果矩阵
a matrix of the same dimension.
维度也是相同的
This is a 3 by
也就是说这两个矩阵
2, both of these are
都是3行2列
3 by 2 dimensional matrices.
这也是3行2列
And by the way,
顺便说一下
you can write multiplication, you know, either way.
你也可以写成另一种方式
So, I have three times this matrix.
这里是3和这个矩阵相乘
I could also have written this
你也可以把这个矩阵写在前面
matrix and 0, 2, 5, 3, 1, right.
1 0 2 5 3 1
I just copied this matrix over to the right.
把左边这个矩阵照抄过来
I can also take this matrix and multiply this by three.
我们也可以用这个矩阵乘以3
So whether it's you know, 3
也就是说
times the matrix or the
3乘以这个矩阵
matrix times three is
和这个矩阵乘以3
the same thing and this thing here in the middle is the result.
结果都是一回事 都是中间的这个矩阵
You can also take a matrix and divide it by a number.
你也可以用矩阵除以一个数
So, turns out taking
那么 我们可以看到
this matrix and dividing it by
用这个矩阵除以4
four, this is actually the
实际上就是
same as taking the number
用四分之一
one quarter, and multiplying it by this matrix.
来和这个矩阵相乘
4, 0, 6, 3 and
4 0 6 3
so, you can figure
不难发现
the answer, the result of
相乘的结果是
this product is, one quarter
1/4和4相乘为1
times four is one, one quarter times zero is zero.
1/4和0相乘得0
One quarter times six is,
1/4乘以6
what, three halves, about six over
结果是3/2
four is three halves, and
6/4也就是3/2
one quarter times three is three quarters.
最后1/4乘以3得3/4
And so that's the results
这样我们就得到了
of computing this matrix divided by four.
这个矩阵除以4的结果
Vectors give you the result.
结果就是是右边这个矩阵
Finally, for a slightly
最后
more complicated example, you can
我们来看一个稍微复杂一点的例子
also take these operations and combine them together.
我们可以把所有这些运算结合起来
So in this calculation, I
在这个运算中
have three times a vector
需要用3来乘以这个向量
plus a vector minus another vector divided by three.
然后加上一个向量 再减去另一个向量除以3的结果
So just make sure we know where these are, right.
让我们先来整理一下这几项运算
This multiplication.
首先第一个运算
This is an example of
很明显这是标量乘法的例子
scalar multiplication because I am taking three and multiplying it.
因为这里是用3来乘以一个矩阵
And this is, you know, another
然后这一项
scalar multiplication.
很显然这是另一个标量乘法
Or more like scalar division, I guess.
或者可以叫标量除法
It really just means one zero times this.
其实也就是1/3乘以这个矩阵
And so if we evaluate
因此
these two operations first, then
如果我们先考虑这两项运算
what we get is this thing
那么我们将得到的是
is equal to, let's see,
我们看一下
so three times that vector is three,
3乘以这个矩阵
twelve, six, plus
结果是3 12 6
my vector in the middle which
然后和中间的矩阵相加
is a 005 minus
也就是0 0 5
one, zero, two-thirds, right?
最后再减去1 0 2/3
And again, just to make
同样地 为了便于理解
sure we understand what is going on here,
我们再来梳理一下这几项
this plus symbol, that is
这里的这个加号
matrix addition, right?
表明这是一个矩阵加法 对吧？
I really, since these are
当然这里是向量
vectors, remember, vectors are special cases of matrices, right?
别忘了 向量是特殊的矩阵 对吧？
This, you can also call
或者你也可以称之为
this vector addition This
向量加法运算
minus sign here, this is
同样 这里的减号表明
again a matrix subtraction,
这是一个矩阵减法运算
but because this is an
但由于这是一个n行1列的矩阵
n by 1, really a three
实际上是3行1列
by one matrix, that this
因此这个矩阵
is actually a vector, so this is
实际上是也一个向量
also vector, this column.
一个列向量
We call this matrix a vector subtraction, as well.
因此也可以把它称作向量的减法运算
OK?
好了！
And finally to wrap this up.
最后再整理一下
This therefore gives me a
最终的结果依然是一个向量
vector, whose first element is
向量的第一个元素
going to be 3+0-1,
是3+0-1
so that's 3-1, which is 2.
就是3-1 也就是2
The second element is 12+0-0, which is 12.
第二个元素是12+0-0 也就是12
And the third element
最后第三个元素
of this is, what, 6+5-(2/3),
6+5-(2/3)
which is 11-(2/3), so
也就是11-(2/3)
that's 10 and one-third
结果是10又三分之一
and see, you close this square bracket.
关闭右括号
And so this gives me a
我们得到了最终的结果
3 by 1 matrix, which is
这是一个3行1列的矩阵
also just called a 3
或者也可以说是
dimensional vector, which
一个维度为3的向量
is the outcome of this calculation over here.
这就是这个运算式的计算结果
So that's how you
所以
add and subtract matrices and
你学会了矩阵或向量的加减运算
vectors and multiply them by scalars or by row numbers.
以及矩阵或向量跟标量 或者说实数 的乘法运算
So far I have only talked
到目前为止
about how to multiply matrices and
我只介绍了如何进行
vectors by scalars, by row numbers.
矩阵或向量与数的乘法运算
In the next video we will
在下一讲中
talk about a much more
我们将讨论一个更有趣的话题
interesting step, of taking
那就是如何进行
2 matrices and multiplying 2 matrices together.
两个矩阵的乘法运算